{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man helped Metellus Pius quell a revolt in present-day Spain led by Quintus Sertorius. He gained power in any land within 50 miles of the Mediterranean Sea with the Lex Gabinia and later led the Optimates to a victory at the Battle of Dyrrhachium. This man’s head was presented to Julius Caesar after he was executed under orders of Ptolemy XIII of Egypt after losing the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, name this Roman general who served in the First Triumvirate with Crassus and Caesar.",
      "answer": "Pompey the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pittsburgh Pirates player Roberto Clemente died in an airplane accident en route to this nation. As a filibuster, William Walker overthrew this country’s government. Violeta Chamorro led this nation in the 1990s, ending a war in which one side was controversially supported by Ronald Reagan’s administration. Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega currently leads, for ten points, what Central American nation with capital Managua?",
      "answer": "Nicaragua"
    },
    {
      "question": "During one campaign, this man’s running mate asked “Who am I? Why am I here?” in a debate’s opening statement. During that campaign, this man claimed that a “giant sucking sound” could be heard as NAFTA funneled jobs to Mexico. This founder of Electronic Data Systems spent $60 million on his campaign, but finished third behind George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this Texan billionaire who ran as an independent in the 1992 Presidential election.",
      "answer": "Henry Ross Perot"
    },
    {
      "question": "Donald McCraig authored a 2007 sequel to this novel about one of its central characters’ exile from Charleston. A confrontation on a staircase in this novel leads to its pregnant protagonist breaking her ribs. This novel ends with the protagonist optimistically stating that “tomorrow is another day”. For ten points, name this Margaret Mitchell novel set in Civil War-era Georgia, whose 1939 film adaptation starred Vivien Leigh as Scarlett O’Hara and is the inflation-adjusted most successful film in box office history.",
      "answer": "Gone with the Wind"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event inspired Charles Perrow’s Normal Accidents, and it was analyzed by the Kemeny commission. A hydrogen bubble was vented into the air four days after this incident, which occurred because of a stuck relief valve in Unit 2. Although nobody died because of this accident near Harrisburg, public reaction to it led to the cancellation of over fifty planned reactors. For ten points, name this 1979 incident in which a Pennsylvania nuclear plant went into partial meltdown.",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island incident or accident, etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave a series of benefit concerts in response to the Great Fire of Hamburg, and his travels withCountessMaried’AgoultinspiredhisYearsofPilgrimage. Heincludedslow“lassan”andfast“friska” sections in a set of nineteen works, the fifteenth which was based on the “Rakoczi March.” Heinrich Heine coined a term to describe the frenzied reception he received in Berlin. For ten points, name this virtuoso Romantic pianist who wrote the Hungarian Rhapsodies and was the subject of a namesake “mania.”",
      "answer": "Franz Liszt or Liszt Ferenc"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was hired by the Muscovy Company to find a route to Japan and China, but ice fields at Svalbard cut his journey. Members of this man’s crew on the Discovery mutinied and left him with his teenage son on a small boat in a body of water now named for him. For ten points, name this English explorer whose expeditions for the Dutch East India Company paved way for the colonization of New York, where a river is also named for him.",
      "answer": "Henry Hudson"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s Moran Hill is home to a Friendship Tower built in 1959, as well as a triumphal arch commemorating the resistance against Japanese rule. The Taedong River flows through this city, passing by the Juche Tower. An unfinished 105-story pyramidal building, Ryugyong Hotel, dominates the skyline of, for ten points, what Asian capital city where Kim Jong-un governs?",
      "answer": "Pyongyang"
    },
    {
      "question": "One ruler of this dynasty beheaded Jafar Yahya, leading to the decline of the Barmakid family. That ruler of this dynasty, Harun Al-Rashid, created the House of Wisdom and gave Charlemagne the elephant Abul-Abbas. This dynasty’s capital, Baghdad, was sacked by the Mongols in 1258. For ten points, name this Islamic caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad dynasty.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Genoese crossbowmen were hacked down by friendly forces while retreating during this battle, and one commander at this battle adopted the motto and crest of the blind King John of Bohemia, who died at this battle. That commander was refused help by his father in this battle, saying “let the boy win his spurs”; those commanders were Edward the Black Prince and Edward III. The dominance of the longbow was confirmed in, for ten points, what first decisive English victory in the Hundred Years War?",
      "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation’s motto, “Deo Vindice,” was developed by Thomas Semmes. The Stone Fleet was sunk to blockade this nation, which had two of its diplomats captured in the Trent Affair. Texas v. White rejected the claim that the U.S. was to recognize this nation, whose only Vice President was Alexander Stephens. For ten points, name this country led by Jefferson Davis which seceded from the Union to spark the U.S. Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Confederate States of America",
          "the Confederacy,",
          "C.S.A."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The H.L. Hunley, one of these vehicles owned by the Confederacy, managed to sink the USS Housatonic, but was destroyed three times before finally abandoned.",
        "answer": "submarines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hosius of Cordoba led the synod that called for the convention of this council, which rejected the Quartodecimans’ dating of Easter. A conflict with the Church of the Martyrs, known as the Meletian schism, was addressed at this meeting, which was convened by Constantine I in 325 AD. For ten points, namethisearlychurchcouncilwhichproclaimedabeliefinGod, Jesus, andtheHolySpiritinitsnamesake “Creed.”",
        "answer": "First Council of Nicaea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This controversy was denounced at the First Council of Nicaea. Propounded by its namesake Alexandrine priest, this doctrine placed the Son subordinate to the Father.",
        "answer": [
          "Arianism",
          "the Arian Controversy"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This emperor initiated the building of the Anio Novus aqueduct, brought the Vatican Obelisk to Rome, and annexed Mauretania. This brother of Agrippina the Younger, Drusilla, and Livilla was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard and Cassius Chaerea, possibly in retaliation for wishing to make Incitatus, his horse, a consul. For ten points, name this nephew and predecessor of Claudius, whose common nickname means “little boot.”",
        "answer": "Caligula or Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This historian and author of On Famous Men detailed Caligula’s insanity in Lives of the Twelve Caesars.",
        "answer": "Gaius Suetonius Tranquillus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country memorializes the death of Syed Nazrul Islam on its Jail Killing day. This country’s first president, Sheikh Mujibur Rahman, created BAKSAL by merging the Krishak Sramik party with the Awami League. In 1971, Yahya Khan launched Operation Searchlight against leaders of what is now this country. Ravi Shankar and George Harrison held the world’s first benefit concert to support refugees from, for ten points, what country that borders India and Myanmar on the Bay of Bengal?",
        "answer": "Bangladesh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to its independence, Bangladesh was what province of a Muslim nation created by the Partition of India?",
        "answer": "East Pakistan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert Hooke first observed the shadows cast by these objects. In 1612, these objects supposedly vanished from Galileo’s sight; in reality, their edge’s plane aligned with Earth. Gaps between these objects were discovered by and named for Giovanni Cassini. For ten points, name these fine grains of ice and rock that form several disks around the sixth planet from the Sun.",
        "answer": "rings of Saturn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Dutch scientist, who also invented the pendulum clock and discovered Saturn’s moon Titan, was the first to identify the “ears” surrounding Saturn as a ring. A NASA probe named for this man was brought to Titan by the Cassini orbiter in 2004.",
        "answer": "Christaan Huygens"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation’s economic ruin in the 1950s led to its genre of “scar” literature. One author from this country described his spiritual journey after learning of his survival from cancer. The protagonist of another novel set in this country was born with a jade piece in his mouth and is destined to marry his cousin despite his true love for another cousin. This country’s Four Great Classical Novels include the Romance of the Three Kingdoms and Water Margin. For ten points, name this country, the birthplace of Nobel laureates Gao Xingjian [sheeng-jee-ahn] and Mo Yan.",
        "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This character’s 72 transformations and ability to jump 108,000 li with a single bound allow him to defend the monk Xuanzang on the Journey to the West. Depictions of this character as a monkey date to the Song Dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Sun Wukong",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prince Bagration stalled for time prior to this battle at the Battle of Sch¨ongrabern, and the plan for one side in this battle was created by Franz von Weyrother. The unfortunate General Mack surrendered at the Battle of Ulm prior to this battle, which saw Marshal Soult lead an assault on the Pratzen Heights. Michael Kutusov was demoted prior to this battle by Tsar Alexander I, who, along with Emperor Franz II, was present at this battle. The Third Coalition and the Holy Roman Empire was dissolved after, for ten points, what Battle of the Three Emperors, an 1805 victory for Napol´eon?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Austerlitz",
          "Battle of the Three Emperors before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Austerlitz led to the signing of a treaty in this city, also known as Pressburg, which was once the capital of Hungary.",
        "answer": "Bratislava"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One candidate in this election year chose Nathan Sanford as his running mate. William Crawford took third in this election, the only election after the Twelfth Amendment to be decided by the House of Representatives. Its fourth-place finisher, Henry Clay, was subsequently named Secretary of State. For ten points, John Quincy Adams was elected President in what year’s election, decried as a “corrupt bargain” by the runner-up, Andrew Jackson?",
        "answer": "Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to the election, William Crawford served in this Cabinet position, also held in the 19th century by Albert Gallatin and Robert Walker.",
        "answer": "Secretary of the Treasury"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Health Care",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Viral disease spread by animal bites, for which Louis Pasteur created a vaccine?",
          "answer": "rabies"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mystic healer employed by Tsar Nicholas II to treat his son’s hemophilia.",
          "answer": "Grigori Yefimovich Rasputin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Research clinic based in Rochester, Minnesota, where Lou Gehrig’s ALS was diagnosed.",
          "answer": "Mayo Clinic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medical research university in Baltimore, whose hospital employed Ben Carson.",
          "answer": [
            "Johns Hopkins Hospital, University,",
            "School of Medicine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Physician’s oath to do no harm, based on the writings of a Greek physician.",
          "answer": [
            "Hippocratic Oath",
            "Hippocrates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease spread in New York by the cooking of Mary Mallon.",
          "answer": "typhoid fever"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek god of medicine, whose snake-entwined rod now symbolizes the practice.",
          "answer": [
            "Asclepius",
            "Rod of Asclepius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Hungarian doctor whose suggestion that doctors wash their hands led to lowered mortality rates for new mothers.",
          "answer": "Ignaz Semmelweis"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The French Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "dynasty that was overthrown.",
          "answer": "Bourbon Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "fortress and prison that was stormed on July 14, 1789.",
          "answer": "Bastille Saint-Antoine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jacobin politician and member of the Committee of Public Safety who was guillotined in the Thermidorian Reaction.",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "period of mass political executions led by that man, which was ended by the Thermidorian Reaction.",
          "answer": "Reign of Terror"
        },
        {
          "question": "vow by representatives of the Third Estate to not disperse until a constitution was written.",
          "answer": [
            "Tennis Court Oath",
            "Serment de Jeu de Paume"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "government overthrown by Napoleon in the coup of 18 Brumaire.",
          "answer": "Directory"
        },
        {
          "question": "town where the royal family was recognized while attempting to flee to Austria.",
          "answer": "Varennes"
        },
        {
          "question": "public field where the National Guard massacred anti-royal protesters in 1791.",
          "answer": "Champ de Mars Massacre"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Xerxes the Great",
      "prompt": "Name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the Greek city-state that lost 300 soldiers under King Leonidas to Xerxes at Thermopylae.",
          "answer": "Sparta or Lacedaemon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Xerxes’ “Great” father, who also invaded Greece.",
          "answer": [
            "Darius I",
            "Darius the Great"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the empire ruled by Xerxes.",
          "answer": "Persia or Achaemenid Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "the capital city where he built the Gate of All Nations.",
          "answer": "Persepolis"
        },
        {
          "question": "the strait separating Thrace from Asia that Xerxes crossed on a pontoon bridge.",
          "answer": [
            "Hellespont",
            "Dardanelles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the naval battle fought by Xerxes’ fleet simultaneously with the Battle of Thermopylae.",
          "answer": "Battle of Cape Artemisium"
        },
        {
          "question": "the general that Xerxes left in Greece in 479 BC, who then lost at Plataea.",
          "answer": "Mardonius"
        },
        {
          "question": "the bodyguard who assassinated Xerxes in 465 BC.",
          "answer": "Artabanus"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state’s second governor, Edward Coles, stood down pro-slavery “Egyptians” from this state’s southern third. Even with protection from this state’s governor, Thomas Ford, Joseph Smith was killed in this state’s town of (20 pts)",
        "Carthage. One politician from this state noted “I believe this government cannot endure, permanently, half (10 pts)",
        "slave and half free” in his “House Divided” speech. For ten points, name this state represented in Congress for one term by Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "Illinois"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the course of trying to cover up this event, Mendel Rivers called helicopter pilot Hugh Thompson a traitor for ordering his men to shoot Americans committing this event. President (20 pts)",
        "Nixon pardoned Charlie Company officer William Calley for his murder of 22 people, including (10 pts)",
        "children, during this event. For ten points, name this March 16, 1968 event in which hundreds of Vietnamese citizens were killed by U.S. soldiers, named for one of the villages attacked."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "My Lai Massacre",
        "Son My Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Warning: two answers required. One of these two countries was aided by the New Model Army against the other country at the Battle of the Dunes. The Duc d’Enghein switched sides to command the army of one of these countries, which he had earlier defeated at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Rocroi in the service of the other. One of these countries tried to place Phillip of Anjou on the throne of the other after the death of (10 pts)",
        "Charles II, resulting in a Bourbon alliance. For ten points, the Treaty of the Pyrenees was signed by what two countries, one of whose namesake succession war was started by the other’s Louis XIV."
      ],
      "answer": "France and Spain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group suffered heavy causalities while taking Hamburger Hill during the Vietnam War. Bad weather led to greater than expected casualties for this group during its Mission Albany, the precursor to Operation Neptune. During Operation Market Garden, this group secured (20 pts)",
        "“Hell’s Highway.” Their commanding officer, Anthony McAuliffe, replied “Nuts!” when asked to give up (10 pts)",
        "Bastogne during the Battle of the Bulge. For ten points, name this American light infantry division, also used by President Eisenhower to desegregate Little Rock Central High School in 1957."
      ],
      "answer": "101st Airborne Division"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist painted Pitt the Elder collapsing after giving a speech protesting American independence in his Death of the Earl of Chatham and painted General George Augustus Elliot on horseback pointing towards burning (20 pts)",
        "Spanish ships in The Siege of Gibraltar. He painted his half-brother with a pet rodent in (10 pts)",
        "Boy With a Squirrel, and depicted the rescue of a man who was attacked by the title animal in the Havana Harbor. For ten points, name this 18th century American painter of Watson and the Shark."
      ],
      "answer": "John Singleton Copley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state in 2012, Marissa Alexander fired a “warning shot” at her estranged husband. An unarmed resident of this state’s city of Sanford was shot by George (20 pts)",
        "Zimmerman; in the ensuing trial, the defense did not invoke this state’s 2005 “Stand Your Ground” law, as Zimmerman instead claimed self-defense against (10 pts)",
        "Trayvon Martin. For ten points, name this state where the Stand Your Ground law was expanded in 2014 by Governor Rick Scott."
      ],
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s theory of “conatus” refers to the universal drive that humanity has towards an essential being. He claimed that natural law principles prevented the existence of miracles, and he controversially claimed that Ezra, not (20 pts)",
        "Moses, wrote the Torah. He equated Nature with God, helping lead to his exclusion from a community of conversos, (10 pts)",
        "Jews who had fled the Portuguese Inquisition for Amsterdam. For ten points, name this 17th century Dutch philosopher and author of Ethics."
      ],
      "answer": "Baruch Spinoza"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A friend of this man was beheaded when they attempted to flee his country, possibly to defect to George II of Britain. This monarch created an alliance of German princes called the Furstenbund and oversaw the First (20 pts)",
        "Partition of Poland. The death of Empress Elisabeth led this ruler to sign a peace treaty with Peter the Great in a conflict where his army won at Rossbach, which he began by invading Saxony. His Anti-Machiavel influenced (10 pts)",
        "Voltaire to correspond with this monarch who also invited J.S. Bach to Potsdam. For ten points, name this leader of Prussia during the Seven Years War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Frederick II of Prussia Frederick the Great",
        "Frederick IV of Brandenburg"
      ]
    }
  ]
}